and we are back with the best damn talk
show
in the world i'm lisa and with my
partner john kiriakou
202 521 1320 is the number to call
sometimes we take calls during guest
segments sometimes we get them sometimes
they don't
and 105.5 fm am 1390
is what you're listening to if you're
listening on a radio which is doubtful
i'm just saying most people uh we have
plenty of radio listeners
yeah we do i'm just saying that radio is
a medium john
i'm so glad we're on it oh my gosh i i
am too you know
when when brian and i were doing loud
and clear
he was he mentioned to me several times
how surprised he was
that taxi drivers would tell him that
they listened to our show
so yeah a lot of people do listen on
terrestrial radio
i noticed that on lyft and uber even
ride sharing services
when i drive around i just that wasn't a
dig on our listenership john
there was a dig on radio as a media you
know what i'm saying right
radio's an uh an old fangled is that a
word
old because you're gonna have newfangled
yes yes
it's oldfangled and i again i like it so
there we go
joining us now great friend of the show
smart guy our key correspondent
author caleb is joining us hey caleb how
you doing today
i'm good how about yourself how was how
are both of you good thank you
thanks for coming back i saw easy rider
over the weekend so i am
i'm groovy yeah thanks for asking oh
that's a bit of a pessimistic kind of
new left film from the
late 60s right yeah it is one of my
favorite movies though yeah
a little dark it it sure ends dark oh
boy does it man
the first time i saw it i was like
you've got to be kidding me
everybody in the theater was shocked i
could tell john
oh they hadn't seen it before i'm
guessing some of them hadn't
because i could just tell there was a
parlor over the
wow how were the people yeah let's let's
talk about something
uh happy and fun like the situation in
haiti and cuba
okay so i was saying earlier on the show
we're talking
cuba the protests there we're all over
the news
especially if your news channel of
choice is
fox they were all over it communist
cubia communist cuban communist cuba
and what i said was haiti has been
having protests
for years and they're supported by the
us
and i think that people are i'm i'm sure
things aren't great for the people in
cuba
but they aren't great for the people in
haiti and
uh i just think it's a double standard
caleb what's your take on what's going
on you couldn't have missed this news
over the weekend so what's your take on
the on do you think it's a double
standard
oh well it's a couple things but yes i
mean people in haiti have been marching
and protesting against moise and
u.s media said nothing about it until
moise got killed
um and now all of a sudden you know u.s
media is like catching up and letting
people know oh yeah there's been this
rebellion going on in the country for
the past several months
uh there's also been massive
anti-austerity protests in chile and
argentina
and we heard nothing about it in u.s
media but what's particularly
interesting about these recent protests
in cuba
is that uh you know we heard about them
they started
and the day they started immediately all
kinds of people were out in the streets
uh in miami all kinds of people were out
in the streets
in in new york city and central park and
you know
the cuban american exile community was
out in the streets
protesting in solidarity with these
protests they were blasted all over the
media they're going after bernie sanders
how come he doesn't you know he's not
you know condemning the cuban government
right now the white house has put out a
statement
you know these people have been in the
streets for less than 24 hours and u.s
media is in overdrive supporting them
plus but here's here's the real catch
okay
if you know anything about cuba you'll
know that there's an economic blockade
on cuba
and this this is not like this is not
like a little thing
right if you if you if you make cupcakes
in germany
and you want to send those cupcakes to
the united states you have to sign a
document
certifying that there is not one ounce
of cuban sugar in those cupcakes
uh and if you violate that you can lose
your ability to export to united states
i mean these sanctions on cuba these
the economic blockade is very very very
serious and especially during covid
uh it was particularly hard for cuba to
get the medicine it needed and such
so there's an economic blockade on cuba
and now we have a situation where
there's you know some people in the
country that feel like the way you know
things are being handed out
is not good like there's some government
mismanagement or whatever so they're
protesting
um and so now you know all of the all of
the anti-castro folks
you know that say that they are
concerned about the cuban people they're
taking to the streets
so you'd think they're saying we're
concerned about the cuban people uh they
don't get you know they don't have the
medicine they need and all that you
would think they'd be saying
so lift that blockade you know like lift
that blockade help them get the medicine
they need they're protesting because
they need medicine they need
they need to deal with some food
shortages and stuff so let's open up the
blockade
that is not their message i talked on
good authority to people who went to
central park and talked to them
that was not their message at all they
want to toughen up the sanctions they
want a
a tougher approach to cuba they want to
end diplomatic relations between the usa
and cuba so they're
claiming to support the cuban people
while they call for
an escalation uh and and making it
harder to get the medicine and food
supplies and basically exacerbating the
very things that these
protesters are protesting the whole
thing is really really really confused
and it looks to me like there's a lot of
people in miami that have a bone to bic
bone to pick with fidel castro that
aren't particularly concerned about the
situation on the ground they just want
the the commies out of there you know
this is old cold war right-wing fanatic
folks and uh and they're using this
opportunity where they're they're you
know there's some division in the
country there's some frustration and
then there's probably some legit
grievances there
they're using that uh to feed a foreign
policy agenda that's what it looks like
to me
well let me ask you uh about that too
there was a there was a piece in the new
york times this morning saying that
that biden and the democrats are going
to have to tread lightly in florida
in light of what's happening in cuba
because there are so many cuban
um americans and they they sort of trend
conservative in in florida
but i i'm not sure i believe that
i'm not sure that i believe that this is
going to be a challenge for the
democrats
what do you think john just really
willing
how what does that mean yeah well and
and that was part of the problem that i
had with this piece lee
is that they didn't say how like what is
that supposed to mean you can't just
throw this idea into the
middle of the room and have everybody
just nod their heads
if this is a legitimate uprising if this
is the beginning of a legitimate
revolution
in cuba well then that's that's good for
everybody
except maybe the communist party's
leadership
but you know treading lightly no what
you do
is you make an announcement that you
want the best for the cuban people
sorry well indeed but everything
surrounding cuba is just so politically
loaded in the united states
another thing i might add is you know in
response to these protests
uh the cuban communist party they called
on all of their supporters to pour into
the streets and the protests
you know supporting the communist party
supporting the president
have been like 10 times as big as the
protests opposing them
and u.s media is pretty silent on that
um and it's particularly interesting
because this this shows one of the
political strengths
of the cuban communist party which is
that you know back in the
old soviet union the way they dealt with
dissidents was they generally just
ignored them
until they created enough of the problem
that they were just kind of dragged away
and disappeared in the middle of the
night
um right and that created an atmosphere
where average people were afraid to get
involved
in politics right but in cuba especially
starting in the 80s during what they
called the rectification campaign
they had the opposite approach when
there'd be somebody that was was
spouting anti-communism or spouting
pro-american sentiments
they would actually mobilize their
supporters to go debate the person and
argue with them and they were they
kind of brought the population into the
political process as their response
and that has been a lot of their
strength is that you know they have
these
these neighborhood committees the
committee to defend the revolution the
cdr
every building every apartment building
every every
every block and every neighborhood is
very well organized and
i almost wonder i i don't i wouldn't
call this a full-blown color revolution
because i don't i don't think they have
the strength on the ground to actually
pull this off i always feel like this is
a test run
this is this is like how much can we
make the cuban communists miserable
let's see how far we can push it that's
what i think this is
i i agree completely this is not a
revolution
i think it's a test run as well
yeah and obviously
and that's why i point out the hypocrisy
well you know
we noticed this during the uh summit
between putin
and biden everyone who was on the show
uh and and us
caleb all thought that the press
was so much more rabid that's the word
i'll use john is that fair
were they rabid yeah i don't think
technically there was no
foam there was no phone close oh yeah we
get the idea
the press was more rabid about that
about
uh opposing putin then biden himself was
and uh now we see
to no one's surprise exactly you know
fox is
i literally got four alerts in a few
hours about this over the weekend john
from fox yep and you would have thought
it was on
like this is it you know
revolution's here and then i looked at
the footage and i'm like there's some
people protesting
but as you're pointing out caleb the the
pro
cat the pro communist party i would
almost say
procaster that'd be tricky but the
pro-communist party
protests are significantly bigger so of
course
that will be used to prove that it's a
police state right caleb
that they're only out because they're
afraid
yeah i mean that'll be the response
that's the standard analysis and
i mean i'll tell you as somebody who has
has been to many countries that are
described as authoritarian by the u.s
leaders i mean
that's ridiculous i mean the notion that
all these people are just out there
because you know the government made
them and if they don't go out they'll be
you know killed and dragged into a
prison camp or something
let's be realistic okay i mean cuba
doesn't have the level of freedom of
speech that we have in the united states
etc there are human rights concerns but
to make the claim that all these people
are demonstrating at the point of a gun
i think that's pretty absurd
yeah i agree i agree it's absurd
and and this is a two-day event you know
just like the demonstrations in
nicaragua i've been following these
demonstrations in nicaragua they started
off because
because of a shortfall in the social
security system and they
uh the government raised the price of
bread and you know if you're poor
and the price of bread goes up that's a
pretty big deal
but this social security thing was a
very big problem and it began to weaken
the government of daniel ortega
so the election comes up there's
supposed to be an election this year
and so far eight opposition leaders that
is the leaders
of eight opposition parties so far have
been
arrested and imprisoned so now there's
nobody to run against ortega
now to me that necessitates
a real honest-to-god uprising
but in cuba i think you're right this is
a test run
they're going to gauge the government's
reaction the government
if they're smart they're going to try to
institute some
reforms and then we see what happens six
months from now
yeah i i think you're right um
and you know the cuban president has met
with some of the protesters already
and uh we shall see what's going on here
you know i don't know how many times
i've heard that the cuban government
was about to fall in my life i mean
fidel castro tripped
a a decade or so ago and they said it
was over
and then fidel castro actually died and
then they said it was over and then they
implemented some economic reforms where
you know
some cab drivers had to go get a new job
or something and then they said it was
over
and i mean i'm just i've heard it's
gonna it's about to fall the cuban
government's been about to fall in my
whole life
yeah absolutely true okay now let's get
let's get into a slightly heavy topic
caleb it's kind of like the chinese
economy
yeah okay yeah it is and
and this actually sort of relates to
that in the sense that let's talk about
capitalism communism and automation
that idea uh so for a long time
one of the arguments that that pro free
market people would make
is that there was a effect of
where when new technology would come
some
people uh would say well that's getting
rid of jobs
so for instance we used to have elevator
operators
all operators were operated by a person
then we got automatic elevators
and and again that was a long time you
know 100 years ago something like that
and and people would make more than that
actually
if i think about i wasn't around but
what people who are pro free market
would say is look
the elevator operator was replaced
but there are new jobs in manufacturing
for instance automatic elevators and so
on and so forth
now and a friend of mine said this a
while ago
uh a friend of mine had been reading
marks
and she hadn't read marx before and she
was a a liberal
democrat liberal liberal but in
progressive and
she said it's interesting reading marx
she said
because as an economist i don't know i
don't think he's very good
but as a futurist he was spot on with a
lot of stuff
and the the situation marx described
that would evolve that's actually come
to pass
and now we're at a point i think with
automation
even tucker carlson another story there
john about yeah we haven't talked about
that
we even talked about that yeah but but
even tucker carlson came out
about a year or so ago and said that
self-driving trucks for instance are
going to kill the trucking industry
in a way just won't recover from and
even the machines
are being built by other machines now
john that's what's that
that is what's happening yeah so there's
no replacement
theory so again it's a big broad topic
caleb what's your take on it
well it's interesting because a lot of
people have kind of a caricature
of marxism and socialism in their head
now they have this idea that you know
socialist communists they're people who
think that you know some people are rich
and some people are poor
and this is unfair uh and it's just not
fair and we want to make everybody equal
or something
no actually people have been saying that
for a long time uh you know you can go
back to spartacus and ancient rome
i mean you know plato's republic there's
nothing new about that
what made marxism unique was that
marxism had a particular analysis of
history right the history is like a
train
speeding forward you have
hunter-gatherer civilization eventually
get the slave empires of greece and rome
and egypt and mesopotamia
and eventually you get feudalism and out
of feudalism comes capitalism
and capitalism will eventually be
replaced with this higher mode of
production called socialism
and eventually socialism gives way to
this higher even higher mode of
production
called communism which is a world of
vast material abundance where there's so
much
so much wealth being created and so
little human labor is necessary
uh that everyone can kind of just take
what they need and do what they feel
like doing
uh mark said that this you know this
higher stage of communism would be a
society where
labor is life's prime want rather than a
necessity meaning people work because
they feel like it
um but the main point that marx makes
about capitalism
is that capitalism is unstable and
capitalism is irrational
because the capitalist is constantly
driving to produce as many goods as he
can
but pay as little as he possibly can to
do it he wants to
lower his production costs and maximize
his profits
and the result of that is that the
worker who is also the consumer
can't buy back the product that he
produces and pretty soon you have a glut
in the market a glut of over production
um and karl marx talks about this
problem of overproduction
uh and he also talks about how
technological leaps exacerbate it with
what he called the tendency of the
falling rate of profit
and that uh that when you have a big
technological leap
uh the result is a massive economic
crisis and
if you look at the history of the 20th
century it pretty well panned out world
war one came after
some great big technological leaps that
resulted in some pretty big
economic crises world war ii came after
you know henry ford and his great
assembly line
innovations that really changed the way
factory production worked
and the result was uh the great
depression which ultimately led to world
war
ii and that the scary thing about this
marxist understanding which you know no
one says this stuff better than jack ma
by the way the ceo of alibaba the
billionaire he goes around
explaining this uh you know the the tech
optimism mixed in with the tech concerns
uh you know the scary thing about it is
that we're living
in the middle of the biggest
technological leap in a long time
uh you know i mean we have not seen
anything like this 3d printers
artificial intelligence i mean this is
this is astronomical and the result is
going to be
millions and millions of people who have
no place at the assembly line
around the world there's going to be
less and less of a demand for workers
there's going to be increased poverty
and there's going to be an increased
amount of monopolistic stagnation
as a few big corporations uh survive
during the
economic turmoil and the rest kind of go
under um and this
is you know this is what marks analyzed
capitalism this is the process of
capitalism and decay the capitalist
wants to revolutionize technology
and the result is a problem and the
argument is that in a rational society
something like self-driving cars would
be a good thing i mean there's less work
for everybody to do
but only under capitalism where the
worker can only survive so long as he
sells his labor to a boss
under capitalism abundance and
efficiency
creates poverty and getting rid of that
and having a rationally organized
economy where profits are not in command
but there's a state central plan
dictating production can lead to an
uninterrupted state of growth
and if you look at china you know they
do have a market sector but at the end
of the day it's the chinese communist
party that's in charge not the market i
mean you know
they the private companies they go to
them and say you do this and they do it
and they've been able to have a pretty
long string of economic growth because
they're not subject to the irrationality
of the boom bust cycle and over
production and the tendency of the
falling rate of profit etc because
they've overcome the rule of profits
they're able to have longer growth
that's marxism and that's something that
many people don't understand
interesting yeah no i i agree
i agree with caleb's uh analysis i i
think you're exactly right and something
that
that not a lot of people either
understand or
have put a great deal of thought into
but i think you've hit it on the head
so let me say this you know what would
be great john think about this
we need to get mark frost and caleb on
at the same time
oh that's a good idea because
you know this goes to the point and
because i don't agree with everything
caleb's saying
but it's not my job to come on and
bicker with everybody
and but i said it before and i'll say it
again the dude is smart
and the point he's and i also don't
disagree with everything he's saying
and i think when he points out the
subject ma saying for instance
or the thing i'll relate to and tell me
if i'm wrong to relate it
to he's no longer you know he's not
going to be the mayor of new york
but andrew yang bringing up a guaranteed
income for instance
guaranteed income the one of the reasons
i think it actually needs to be
considered now
is the technological reasons that people
like jackman
and and and you and me and
a lot of people we're talking about
because of this great technological leap
so first off do you do you think
relating uh as a
sort of modern solution to the modern
problem of technology
something like a guaranteed basic income
uh makes you know is
is an idea that more and more people
will be thinking about talking about
debating caleb
well look i am not opposed to universal
basic income
but there are a number of different
models of it that have been drawn up i
mean there's not just one theory of it
and you know one concern that i have
about universal basic income
is that you know some of the folks who
are the biggest advocates of it
have been advocates of neo-liberal
economics milton friedman even wrote
about the need for a universal basic
income
not because he thought that everyone
should get an income but he said look if
we have to have a welfare state
should we have a government department
of welfare and a government department
of unemployment insurance and you know
food stamps and
or why don't we just have everybody
everyone no matter
what your job situation how much or what
your life is you get an automatic bank
transfer a thousand bucks a month
and then we can lay off all the people
in the department of labor and all the
people in the uh the department of
agriculture and all the people in the in
the welfare departments get rid of all
those good-paying government jobs that
are you know costing the taxpayer too
much
and everyone just gets a bank transfer
and then we can carry out mass austerity
and shrink the size of the government
and the economic consequences of that
would be quite concerning i mean if you
think about
how many people are involved in
administering the welfare state and
they're all
working for a living and they're all you
know getting a decent paycheck and if
you took that
out of the economy and that you know you
took that out right and it was just kind
of well everyone gets an automatic
transfer of 10 000
a month no questions asked um i think
you know there could potentially be
an issue and the other thing that
concerns me right so if you're going to
get rid of food stamps you're going to
get rid of you know
you know section 8 for rent you're going
to get rid of all of that and everyone
just gets a bank transfer
all it takes is one state to say hey why
should convicted pedophiles get you know
a thousand dollars a month
and then they pass a law that says okay
well you know convicted pedophiles don't
get it
you know and then it's gone and then
we've got thousands of convicted
pedophiles
with no income whatsoever who are out on
the streets starving and potentially
rioting
and once you do it to them then you can
do it to anyone who's been convicted of
a violent crime
and then you can do it to anyone who
doesn't pay their taxes and pretty soon
you're going to have a mob of people who
don't have anything nothing and that
concerns me i i there are some concerns
about it but the premise that everyone
gets a basic income
i'm not opposed to it just depends how
you implement it many different models
have been proposed
yeah yeah you know it's funny too that
uh that
that argument didn't fly the universal
basic
basic universal income argument didn't
fly in the new york mayoral race
when yang brought it up uh just after he
announced his uh
his candidacy the the new york times
thought it was a great idea and said
that he could actually win this thing
right there was a fawning
tribute to him about six months ago and
i think he ended up coming in
what fourth people just weren't buying
into it
well i think andrew yang had the
opposite problem in the new york
election is that he sounded like a
boring
normal politician i thought who is this
guy you know i mean when he was running
for president he was you know
the math hats and the wild ideas and
stuff and i heard him in new york i
thought this just sounds like
you know another bill de blasio i mean
he was totally uninteresting if he had
if he had made the universal basic
income and that more part of his
campaign i think he would have done
better
yeah like i said to me i think it's
interesting i think it's gonna be
something that people
i think the point you're making caleb is
right on
there are different variants and that's
why i think john it's going to be
debated
for you know it's they're going to try
to figure out it should be debated
yeah i agree with you it should be
debated you don't have to like it
but we should be talking about it and by
the way i remember the director john
carpenter
in 1974 directed a very scary movie
about the pedophile riots
of 2022. no he didn't i just made that
up but
but you get a picture of john can't you
okay hey caleb we're almost out of time
let me ask you this
would you be open to having a i don't
like the word debate because i don't
want people bickering
conversation conversation with a
libertarian economist
mark frost yes okay john i think
caleb and mark had to debate who would
win
answer the audience yeah you know what
that that that's right the audience
that's right no i really mean it yeah
there's two very smart very reasonable
people that we like
that'd be great yes hey hey caleb tell
people what you're working on do you
have anything coming up
that people should be looking out for
either in books or on rt
or wherever well my latest book bread
tube serves imperialism which is a
critique of this left-wing youtube
community is the
is the number one new release on
amazon.com in the category of anarchism
right now i've never had a book sell so
well so if people want to see uh hear a
critique
from an actual marxist of these liberal
uh internet commentators they should
check out my new book bread tube serves
imperialism
it's getting good reviews excellent hey
caleb that's been
congratulations by the way that's
fantastic and just shows the capitalism
works because your book's
very successful i'm just messing with
you
okay cattle muffins joining us thanks
again to mark frost
hey rod let's seriously let's set up
this discussion because i think it would
be
john i really mean it right that'd be
great no i think it's a terrific idea
there we go
and thanks to our interpreter producer
rod thanks to the great saul
and thanks for all the great calls today
brave ingrid
grief and owl killer we'll be back
tomorrow i'm liz stranahan with my
partner john kiriakou
this is the back story dig it
you